let's have a look now at techniques
for efficient virtualization so this is
how the hypervisor type one works when you have
virtualization technology so we have the hardware
on top of that we have the hypervisor and then
on top of that we have the guest operating system
and on top of that the user processes now
we need to distinguish between real
user and kernel mode and virtual user and kernel
mode so the real kernel mode is the one in which
the hypervisor will run because the hypervisor is
operating directly on the hardware so it can run
of course also privileged instructions
and all the rest will be user mode from
the perspective of the hypervisor but if you
look inside the guest operating system then
you can distinguish between kernel and user
mode there too in this case we refer to them
as virtual modes
now if there is virtualization technology
you know you have a bitmap you can use to set
the different interrupts you want to result
in the hypervisor taking control so
it works as I mentioned before now we said
that virtualization was there even before
2005 when this technology was introduced so how
was it done before? now we're going to have a
look at that and actually we're going to see that
some previous techniques might still be efficient
and used even with the presence of modern
virtualization hardware so when we started the course
I mentioned that there are these two modes
the kernel and the user mode with the bit
but in the slides it's also mentioned that there
is hardware that supports more levels of privilege
so in practice usually you have four different
privilege levels and these are called rings
numbered from zero to three in this case okay
so without virtualization but also
when you run the operating system directly
on the hardware what it's usually done
is that you use two of these rings ring zero
which is the lowest one for the operating
system because it can run privileged
instructions and then the highest one you use
it for the processes so you don't really use the
remaining two but the remaining two can be used
when you want to use virtualization
so you can put the hypervisor
at level zero the user process
you leave it at the level
four so at ring number three and then you can place
the guest operating system
at ring one so it does not have access to all
privileged instructions which is good because
we still want the hypervisor to wake up as a
result of an interrupt when the guest operating
system or the user process is trying to execute
privileged instructions but it allows to get more
power to the operating system because it can
differentiate now between who is the operating
system which can run instructions that can be
run within the level of privilege of rank 1 and
the user processes the other processes that are
ring 3 now this does not really solve the problem
of sensitive instructions so what was done before
and it's still sometimes being used for efficiency
is basically to
rewrite recompile the code so that sensitive
instructions are removed a basic block
it's a sequence of instructions that so it's
it's the set of following (consecutive) instructions
that can be run by the hypervisor but
that belong to the operating system and they
are a sequence of instructions that ends with
a branch read the chapter in the book for more
details about this but basically it means it's a
set of instructions that doesn't have a jump to
a different function so it's a sequential
series of instructions so what happens is that
the hypervisor before giving control to what is
above the hypervisor so the guest operating system
it scans the next block and replaces all sensitive
instructions there so that it can gain control
whenever these are basically executed and thus
preventing the problem of having these sensitive
instructions that can behave differently
between the operating system and the user
process but it would not be detected without
the virtualization technology so why do we
still use this approach even if we have hardware
that supports virtualization? because you know
that everything involved in a trap or an interrupt
that requires waking up a different process as a
result of an invocation of a privileged function
and so on it's always a costly operation
there might be cases in which rewriting the set of
instructions you are going to run performs better
than actually being interrupted
every time they try to access a
sensitive instruction or privileged
instruction and that's why this
approach is still used and actually you can
even use it for privileged instructions so
imagine that you're running a piece of code and
in this piece of code you see that you might end
up disabling interrupts and then enabling them
again and maybe do this several times if you go
for standard virtualization technology it will
work but every time you want to disable or enable
you need to wake up the hypervisor and then let
the hypervisor emulate the desired behavior taking
care of actually interacting with the hardware and
not messing up stuff for the other guest operating
systems that could be run at the same time on
the other hand it might perform better to just
translate sort of recompile if you want the
set of instructions you are going
to execute and maybe replace all the
sensitive ones or the privileged ones in
this case that are trying to disable interrupts
with an if statement so you can embed the
behavior of the hypervisor directly into the code
you are going to run so that instead of waking up
the hypervisor each time a call to this privileged
instruction is executed you let directly the
rewritten process operate as the hypervisor would
do because it's the hypervisor who
changes who recreates the set of instructions